all right
[Music]
fibromyalgia is a common disorder whose
Cardinal manifestation is chronic
widespread pain
well not so common affecting two to four
percent of the population though
probably more like two percent uh and
especially women
for decades some medical professionals
dismissed fibromyalgia it's all in
people's heads but this outdated view
has been refuted by more recent research
characterizing it as a disorder of pain
regulation and sensitization brain
Imaging Studies have shown several
perturbations of pain processing and
regulation that amplify pain and people
with a condition twin Studies have shown
that about half of fibromyalgia is
genetic but the other half we can do
something about there are lots of drugs
with lots of side effects to help with
some of the symptoms but what about
lifestyle approaches engagement in
regular physical activity is considered
imperative for Effective management of
fibromyalgia a systematic review of
meta-analysis of randomized clinical
trials on the effectiveness of
therapeutic exercise in fibromyalgia
found that both aerobic and resistance
exercises are effective ways of reducing
pain and improving Global well-being in
people with fibromyalgia patients May
worry and perceive the exercise will
worsen their pain and fatigue and so you
have to start slow work your way up as
tolerated with the goal of eventually
achieving 30 to 60 Minutes of moderate
intensity aerobic exercise in addition
to muscle strengthening exercises one to
three sets of eight to eleven exercises
eight to ten repetitions with a load of
about seven pounds or 45 percent of the
max you can lift
but what about dietary interventions in
terms of dialing down the pain
sensitivity
well what causes it in the first place
inflammation during the inflammatory
response pain receptors are activated
and chronic inflammation can cause
chronic activation which may cause
chronic pain due to this prolonged
hypersensitization of pain pathways
no wonder then that a pro-inflammatory
diet was found to be associated with
pain hypersensitivity in patients with
fibromyalgia syndrome exactly which
foods are pro-inflammatory and which
foods are anti-inflammatory
check out those twin videos but broadly
speaking components of processed foods
and animal products such as saturated
fat trans fat and cholesterol were found
to be pro-inflammatory while
constituents of whole plant foods such
as fiber and phytonutrients were
strongly anti-inflammatory
the intake of dietary fiber found
concentrated only one place whole plant
Foods is fundamental to reducing not
only the risk of abdominal pain but also
muscle and joint pain we think because
of these short chain fatty acids that
are good gut bugs produce when we eat
fiber these short chain fatty acids are
important mediators of pain
fundamentally because they modulate
inflammation so having a lots of fiber
feeding bugs in your colon It's like
carrying around your own
anti-inflammatory compound Factory but
to cultivate them you actually have to
eat the foods that feed them
in terms of phytonutrients
plant-derived polyphenols are widely
acknowledged also act as
anti-inflammatory substances here's some
foods packed with anti-pain pathway
nutrients berries greens Citrus nuts
spices like turmeric and ginger edamame
and green tea that's why you can do
randomized double-blind crossover trials
showing that about three cups worth of
strawberries they can significantly
improve pain and inflammation if that's
what a single plant can do what about a
diet chock full of plant Foods
put people on a strictly plant-based
diet rich in fresh fruits and vegetables
whole grains and various legumes which
are beans would be chickpeas and lentils
as well as nuts and seeds and you can
drop C-reactive protein levels 33
percent in three weeks which is a
leading blood marker of systemic
inflammation but does that translate
into less pain
and the answer is yes when it comes to
migraine headaches yes when it comes to
painful periods a significant reduction
in menstrual pain duration and pain
intensity in addition to premenstrual
symptoms in fact even just a single
plant cinnamon about a third of a
teaspoon three times a day during your
period can help though it doesn't work
as well as ibuprofen ginger powder on
the other hand ground ginger has been
found to be comparable to ibuprofen and
relieving pain in women with painful
cramps you can learn more in my video on
the topic Whole Food plant-based diets
also alleviate the symptoms of
osteoarthritis several Studies have
shown improvements in rheumatoid
arthritis symptoms with diets excluding
animal products though maybe just as
much a function of increasing the
quantity of healthy plant foods but it's
not just because plant-based diets are
so effective in causing weight loss even
at the same weight there's an
improvement in rheumatoid arthritis for
more plant-based diets and plant-based
diets can also alleviate fibromyalgia
symptoms
this is the latest study which enrolled
anyone with chronic musculoskeletal pain
fibromyalgia or not yes diets high in
animal proteins and fats have been
linked to chronic pain and inflammation
while plant-based diets produce
anti-inflammatory responses so did it
actually work when put to the test for
pain yes
consumption of a plant-based diet
produced positive improvements in
chronic pain and function how much well
a minimally clinically important
difference in chronic musculoskeletal
pain is one point on the numeric pain
rating scale which is just a scale of
one to ten on how much pain you're
feeling and on the plant-based diet
perceived pain decreased an average of
three points on a 10 point scale from an
average of five or six out of ten down
to two
now unlike most of the prior studies
there was no control group but what's
the downside of giving healthier eating
a try in fact those with chronic pain
are more likely to be overweight and
have nutrition related maladies such as
high blood pressure diabetes and heart
disease all of which can be prevented
arrested and in some cases even reversed
with a healthy enough plant-based diet
so any pain benefit is just icing on the
cake of Health
scratch that how about the dollop of
guacamole on your bean burrito
[Music]
thank you